If you see this video, that means you
are about to make mistakes that could
cost you 20 years of your musical
journey. But if you have a few minutes,
I'm going to show you how to avoid them.
Now, listen carefully. Why do I say
this? Because the mistakes that you were
planning to make, I've already made them
in my piano journey. Do you ever feel
like this musical instrument thing is
not for you? And whenever you sit down
behind the piano, you are overwhelmed of
what to even practice. This was me and
this feeling actually never goes away.
Even to the people that you think are
pros, remember new level, new devil. But
let me reassure you of one thing.
Everything
begins appearing the
mind. Listen, at the beginning of my
piano journey, I could be watching
someone seeing what they play and I'm
like, man, man, maybe this thing is not
for me. Like I I can't. But that was the
mistake. It was because of the way I was
looking at it. Perception. Now take a
look at the jogger. Now every jogger has
a goal. Let's say they want to hit 5
miles today. Good. Now if this is the
first time they are jogging 5 miles and
they keep their eyes on the destination
of that 5 miles or how far ahead it is,
they're going to be overwhelmed like I I
can't jog. It's too far. But now if they
just keep their eyes a few meters ahead
and just keep jogging. That's all. Keep
jogging. We'll get there. Keep jogging.
That is much better. So that's the first
mistake. You don't focus on the people
who are already far better than you, who
have been playing for 20 years. You
focus on the small steps that you are
supposed to
take. So good. When you finish, go to
court. When you just go according to
your pace, you would get there
eventually. The only way you would never
ever get there is if you quit. That's
all. So, you've got to tell yourself,
you made a promise to yourself and
you're going to stop at nothing until
you learn how to play the instrument,
the piano, whatever instrument that you
are learning. Just remember this, every
great player that you know, struggled
first. Nobody skips that phase in life.
Nobody. So, the next time you sit behind
the piano and then you say, "Oh, no. I'm
not cut out for this. I'll never learn.
I'm not a natural. I don't learn. Just
say this one step at a time. Poco a poco
poco a poco.
Simple. Now learning the piano is very
very fun when you are playing the songs
that you
love.
Wonderful. But do you know the boring
part?
But how is this boring? Some of you may
say, now I want you to imagine this.
Playing
this for
hours, every single
day. The same thing, the basics. I
cannot stress this enough. A lot of
people don't spend a lot of time on the
basics. They like to just I want to go
and learn. I want to calm down the
basics. And what are the basics of
playing the piano? Rhythm, melody,
harmony. Rhythm is a sound and silence
in music in a systematic pattern. Sound,
silence. Sound, silence. Sound,
silence. Yep, that's rhythm. A melody is
the movement of one note to another in a
systematic patterning.
Now this is a melody systematic part. A
harmony is a combination of two or more
notes that is pleasing to the ear. So
this that's a harmony. That's a
harmony. That's a harmony. Now take this
as you this is your level of basics on
the piano. The more you practice the
basics, just the basics, nothing else,
the more this thing right here expands.
This means that the more time you put in
learning the basics, the more you'll be
able to stand the test of time when you
build on it. But when you just learn the
basics haphazardly because you want to
get to playing your favorite songs
immediately, it will catch up to you
that I can assure you you realize that
you're taking too long to learn the
songs that you've always wanted to play.
And that's when you begin to doubt
yourself whether you ever be able to
master the piano. So, one thing my
friend, love the boring. Very important.
The basics are boring. Love it. And
that's what separates the pros from the
normal players. Once you have mastery of
the basics, then you can move on to the
next level. But never neglect the
basics. Very important. Remember, I'm
not saying that you should play the
basics forever. No, no, no, no, no.
But the more you have mastery of the
basics, the more you have mastery of
everything
else. Listen, earlier on when I first
began my piano journey, I thought I
lacked talent because I was learning
difficult things. Then I had this
mindset like, "Oh, maybe I should just
quit the piano. Maybe this piano thing
is not meant for me." But this was the
wrong mindset I was having. When you're
finding it difficult to learn something,
that's actually a good sign. That means
that you're pushing beyond your comfort
zone. Remember I said mindset is
everything in this piano journey. Now
think about it. When you are playing a
song and it feels too easy. Tell me, are
you learning anything new? Probably not.
But when you're playing a song and it's
so difficult, you are sloppy at first
like what's all this? But trust me, you
are learning something. Your brain is
now adjusting to this new thing. Your
fingers are now being exercised beyond
your
capabilities. You are building what we
call muscle memory. Now, here's the
secret. Come closer. When you're
learning something difficult, first of
all, take a deep breath
in. And now find the part that is
difficult. Don't go fast. Go very slow.
Slow. Remember, slow is smooth and
smooth is fast. Play it as slow as
possible. The speed will pick up. Trust
me on this one. So, watch
this. Now, it's going to be a little
challenging to some people. What I did
right here is what I'd like to call
triplets. So, 1 2 3. You understand?
Now, if I play it fast, it's going to be
very
confusing. But if you slow it down, it
is better. Watch.
[Music]
P. That's all. You understand? So go
slow. The speed will pick up. Sometimes
all you need to do is to change your
practice
routine. When I also started learning
how to play the piano, I was all over
the place. See tutorial here, tutorial
there. jump from one song to another 10
songs at you can imagine. So I found out
one thing. The most important thing that
you need is discipline. On the internet,
there's no clear path when you watch
tutorial videos. You just keep spinning
in circles. Here's what I wish someone
told me. Focus on one clear path and
trust the process. You don't need to
master every single tip out there.
Remember, less is more. Pick one course,
one mentor or one structured method and
stick with it. Let me give you a fun
scenario. How many of you know Cyclops
of X-Men? You you know his power, right?
When he's without his glasses, when he
opens his eyes, it just the power is
everywhere. But when he wears his
helmet, that thing or his glasses, his
helmet, he's able to direct the power
here, here, here, here, here. Exactly.
That's what happens when you have a
structured plan in learning the piano.
Even if you say you're going to learn
one song this month, just stick to
learning that song. Don't be jumping
from this song to another. Oh, I've seen
another song. Let no no no no no no no.
Stick to it. Build that focus muscle.
It's very very important in anything
that you do. See, a lot of people are
distracted in this life. So, if you have
this level of focus, it's going to bring
a lot of control in your life and put
you ahead of a lot of
people.
Listen, one of the most discouraging
frustrations that I hear and I've felt
myself is, "Oh, I know how to play with
my right hand very well, but
coordinating with my left hand playing
at the same time is impossible. Maybe
I'm just not meant to play the piano."
Trust me, I understand that feeling.
Now, come closer. I want you to do
something for me right now. I want you
to tap your hand on your head like this
with your right hand. Exactly. Now I
want you to use your left hand to
scratch your chest like
this. You're doing it right. This means
one thing that hand coordination is 100%
learnable. It's not an inborn talent
bestowed on the lucky few. No, no, no,
no, no, no. It's a skill you build
gradually. The key here is to train the
hands separately first. After that, you
join them together and train them, but
slowly. Don't try to speed anything up.
Don't try to go as fast as you went on
your right hand or your left hand. No,
go very slow. You're learning a new
skill. Remember, slow is smooth and
smooth is fast. Go as slow as possible
that you would get it. As time goes on,
you're going to build the skill
gradually. Let me show you something.
So, now this is the datonic scale on
your right hand.
Now this is the datonic scale on your
left
hand. Great. Now combine them together.
What do you
get? It's going to be a little confusing
to some people, but you have to go slow.
Don't speed it up.
The speed will eventually come. Go.
[Music]
Exactly. Now, when you gain control, you
can be able to do something like
[Music]
this. Exactly. When you first begin,
it's going to be messy, but that's okay.
Your brain is now building the
connections between the hands. So, calm
down, relax, take a deep breath in. And
so, whenever you catch yourself saying
that, "Oh, maybe I'm not wired for this.
I can't learn this piano. It's too
difficult." Just say, "I haven't learned
it yet, but I will." H you will because
you will. All is left is time and
practice. Now, come here. I'll let you
on a little secret. Have you ever
thought to yourself, "Oh, me, I don't
know how to create musicals, so me, I'm
not a real musician. I'm not a pianist.
I can't play." Please, I beg you, hear
me out on this one. If you create music
or you play the piano at any level and
it brings you joy, you are a real
pianist or a musician. Being a musician
is not playing fast or certificates or
anything. It's about expression and
growth. I used to think like that when I
began my journey. Oh man, I used to see
all these jazz cards, Oscar, Chico, even
Farrell Williams. Man, I thought I was a
good
faker. Straight up impostor syndrome. If
creating music is your goal, just know
that creativity can be learned and
nurtured. Start small by changing the
notes or chords of a few songs. So with
a song like All of
Me, you can change the progression too.
[Music]
Exactly. It might start basic at first,
but what you are doing right here is
that you are exercising your creative
muscle. Play what you feel. Let your
fingers wonder. The more you experiment,
the more you develop. Own the identity
of a composer. Yes, you are a piano
player. Remember, music is any sound
that sounds pleasing to the ear. Did
what you play right now sound pleasing
to your ear? Good. Then you're a
musician. In the age of social media,
it's very easy to compare yourself to
others. Maybe you see a six-year-old
prodigy piano player playing like crazy.
Then there's you in your late 20s, 30s
or 40s. You might be now thinking, "Ah,
others my age are way ahead of me. I'll
never catch up. Maybe it's too late for
Hey, stop right there." Listen, learning
the piano is not a race. There's no
finish line that you are behind on.
Everyone's circumstance and goals are
different. The truth is, you can start
at any age and make beautiful music. I'm
going to play you a video. Listen to
what he says. So, Jordan, you can learn
to play an instrument at any age. Look
at that. I'm 68 years old. I started
this really when I was 64 years old. You
see, the key here is to focus on your
progress rather than any other person's
progress. Comparison is the thief of
joy. Remember that. Ask yourself, are
you better now than last month? If yes,
that's a win. That's a win. Yes,
somebody who has been playing a piano
for more than 10 years will be ahead of
for about a year. And so what? In fact,
it will shock you that if you learn the
right approach, you surpass people who
have been playing the piano for a long
time who have not been practicing. The
only way to truly fall behind is to
quit. Don't let comparisons or age
anxiety steal the joy of learning this
beautiful instrument. Whether you are 17
or 70, the best time to learn the piano
was yesterday. The second best time is
now. Remember, this is your personal
journey.
It is never too late to make
music. Anything you are doing or you're
working on, don't do it alone. Let me
tell you a secret. When I was first
learning the piano, I was just going
from tutorial here to tutorial there in
random places. Maybe I was too shy or
too proud to admit that I needed help.
But when I met a mentor or I started
rolling with other pianists going the
same direction, my progress just
skyrocketed. Listen to me when I say
this. A good teacher will save you a lot
of time. Trust me, they've made all the
necessary mistakes already. So, they'll
help provide you with three important
things: structure, accountability, and
encouragement. Don't be jumping from one
tutorial to another. Stick to that
teacher's method because the more laser
focused you are on something, the faster
you will get to that goal. Even a
practice partner or an online group can
help make a huge difference. I say this
because I am a product of a mentor.
Listen, it's not that you cannot learn
on your own. Of course, you absolutely
can. But it's a bumpier road. There's no
price for doing things the hardest way.
No. In fact, getting help is not a sign
of
weakness. It's actually smart. So, my
advice, turn practice into progress by
letting someone guide you on a path that
actually works. Well, guys, we've
covered a lot in this episode. I just
want to say that learning the piano is a
journey of transformation, not just
musical skills. The most important thing
about learning the piano is
why. Why do you want to learn the piano?
Ask yourself now. If the why is strong,
the how is easy. Before I wrap up, this
is a warm invitation and preparation.
Depending on when you watch this video,
I always say this. I am coming up with
something that is going to transform
your piano life for good. Just keep your
eyes in the description. And until
then, be creative.